<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Blueschisting - transit</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/transit.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2018-08-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Airport Walking</title><link href="/airport-walking.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-08-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-08-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ian Rose</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-08-18:/airport-walking.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="oakland" src="articles/transit/images/oakland.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I like to walk places (a lot). I also prefer to avoid taking taxis or ridesharing services.
At some point in college, I found myself at the Tweed New Haven airport
at an odd hour, and decided to try my hand at walking downtown rather than
taking a cab.  I found that it was surprisingly pleasant, and the distance
was not outlandish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From then on I have had a quasi-hobby of walking to/from the various
airports that I fly. The general goal is to go between the terminals
and the downtown of whatever city the airport serves (though I will
bend those rules if convenient). Sometimes the walk is fun, sometimes
it is unpleasant, but it always takes me through different parts of the city
than most visitors usually see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few tips for having a successful airport walk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep the weather and time-of-day in mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Travel with only a backpack as luggage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Usually the most dangerous part is the road network around the airport itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you walk from an airport, nobody has to sit next to you on the plane afterwards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plot out a rough route beforehand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's worth it to take a less direct route in order to avoid highways and arterials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is intended to keep a record of the airports from/to which I have walked,
as well as some reviews, in case anybody reading this wants to give it a shot!
I will try to keep this list up to date as I collect more airports.
There is some low-hanging-fruit out there (looking at you, Burbank,
Las Vegas, and San Diego).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New Haven&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As noted, this is the first airport I walked from.
This was a fairly short and pleasant, with low hills and a couple of bridges.
It also passed through
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wooster_Square"&gt;Wooster Square&lt;/a&gt;,
home of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sally%27s_Apizza"&gt;best pizza&lt;/a&gt; to be found anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Distance: 5 miles&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Would I do it again? Yes.&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe data-city="nh" src=/visualization/airports/leaflet_airport.html?lat=41.2912&amp;lon=-72.9179&amp;zoom=13 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Boston&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logan Airport is a tricky place to walk from. It is only about two miles from downtown Boston,
but the only road there is a tunnel under the estuary with no pedestrian access.
So instead I was forced to take the long way around, through Eagle Hill,
the industrial town of Everett, and Charleston.
That route was considerably longer, but did go past
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Bunker_Hill"&gt;Bunker Hill&lt;/a&gt;
and the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USS_Constitution"&gt;USS Constitution&lt;/a&gt;,
and involved three bridges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logan Airport is also at the bottom of the list of pedestrian-friendly airports.
It was &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; difficult to leave without getting hit by a car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Distance: 8 miles&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Would I do it again? Sure.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe data-city="bo" src=/visualization/airports/leaflet_airport.html?lat=42.3714&amp;lon=-71.0584&amp;zoom=13 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;College Station&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boy, there is not a lot in College Station.
But there is a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Texas_A%26M_University"&gt;University&lt;/a&gt;
and an airport, and a straight shot of a road between them.
There weren't really any sidewalks on the road to the airport,
but there also weren't many cars, so the walk was brief and uneventful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Distance: 3 miles&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Would I do it again? Yes.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe data-city="cs" src=/visualization/airports/leaflet_airport.html?lat=30.6115&amp;lon=-96.3502&amp;zoom=14 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;San Jose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mineta Airport is very close to downtown San Jose,
so the walk from the airport was quick and easy.
It was also boring, and has mostly left my brain.
Next time I'll take the &lt;a href="https://www.grpg.org/"&gt;river path&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Distance: 4 miles&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Would I do it again? Yes.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe data-city="sj" src=/visualization/airports/leaflet_airport.html?lat=37.3835&amp;lon=-121.9342&amp;zoom=12 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Philadelphia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philadelphia International was a fun airport to walk from.
The George C. Platt bridge was cool to walk over, if not particularly pedestrian-friendly:
&lt;img alt="platt" src="articles/transit/images/platt.png" title="By Davidt8 - Own work, Public Domain, https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=10874388"&gt;
There are also cheese-steaks to be had on the road,
and one can end up at the Liberty Bell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Distance: 8 miles&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Would I do it again? Sure.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe data-city="ph" src=/visualization/airports/leaflet_airport.html?lat=39.9305&amp;lon=-75.195236&amp;zoom=12 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Oakland&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey, this one is a straight-up nice walk: nice enough that I have done it twice.
The bulk of it goes across the odd estuary community of Bay Farm Island
(formerly, but not currently an island),
and Alameda island (currently, but not formerly an island).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bay Farm had previously been a known as Asparagus Island (for its principal crop),
but then it was developed for residential use, and was connected
to the mainland via the fill that became the Oakland Airport, rendering both of its names incorrect.
Now it is mostly a sleepy community with some really fun canals criss-crossing it:
&lt;img alt="bay-farm-1" src="articles/transit/images/bay-farm-1.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="bay-farm-2" src="articles/transit/images/bay-farm-2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alameda, on the other hand, used to be attached to the mainland,
but was made into an island with the dredging of the Oakland estuary.
The walk along it's southern beach is quite pleasant:
&lt;img alt="alameda" src="articles/transit/images/alameda.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only downside of the Oakland airport walk is at the end:
crossing the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Posey_and_Webster_Street_tube"&gt;Posey tube&lt;/a&gt;
to the mainland is no fun at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Distance: 10 miles&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Would I do it again? Definitely.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe data-city="oak" src=/visualization/airports/leaflet_airport.html?lat=37.7637&amp;lon=-122.2634&amp;zoom=12 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Los Angeles (incomplete)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not completed the walk from LAX: I got as far as Culver City.
The main takeaways from this unfinished effort are the Westchester is a lovely neighborhood,
and that LAX is (surprisingly enough) among the more pedestrian accessible airports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Distance: 8 miles&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Would I do it again? Absolutely, I want to finish it.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe data-city="lau" src=/visualization/airports/leaflet_airport.html?lat=34.0236&amp;lon=-118.3530&amp;zoom=12 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Seattle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The walk from SeaTac Airport is among the more varied of the airport walks
that I have done. It goes through suburbia, industrial Seattle, and some
surprisingly exurban areas, before ending up downtown.
All the while, you get glimpses of Mount Rainier, and the various
Seattle waterways are never far. All in all a pretty fun walk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Distance: 12 miles&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Would I do it again? Sure, given enough time.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe data-city="sea" src=/visualization/airports/leaflet_airport.html?lat=47.5330&amp;lon=-122.2730&amp;zoom=11 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;San Francisco&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one took two tries to get right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time I tried to walk from SFO
I tried to go along the Bay, past Brisbane. Unfortunately, none
of the handful of roads that go that way have sidewalks, and all have
extremely fast traffic. It was hot out, and eventually I got tired of cars zooming past me
by the Brisbane Lagoon.
I hopped on Muni in Visitacion Valley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second time I tried to walk from SFO, I decided to go the more pedestrian-friendly route:
over San Bruno Mountain. This involved no cars, but did involve climbing over
a 1000 foot peak (which is more than one typically does in these airport walks):
&lt;img alt="san-bruno" src="articles/transit/images/san-bruno.jpg" title="View from the top towards downtown SF"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other side of the mountain, it's pretty straightforward to pick up Mission Street
and take it the whole way downtown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, the walk from SFO is challenging but rewarding.
Take San Bruno.
Also, there are good burritos to be had in South San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Distance: 15 miles&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Would I do it again? Yes, given enough time.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe data-city="sf" src=/visualization/airports/leaflet_airport.html?lat=37.7126&amp;lon=-122.4076&amp;zoom=12 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New Orleans&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, I screwed this one up.
I walked from Carrollton to New Orleans International,
across miles and miles of suburbia. It was mostly hot and boring,
although Lafreniere Park was enjoyable:
&lt;img alt="lafreniere" src="articles/transit/images/lafreniere.jpg" title="Lots of ducks"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then when I arrived at the airport, I learned that I had walked to the
wrong &lt;em&gt;side&lt;/em&gt; of the airport.
And so it came to pass that I walked around the airport, on a grassy strip
between a highway and a runway. I do not recommend this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="msy" src="articles/transit/images/msy.png" title="An unpleasant walk"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The worst part is this: you could do this entire walk along the levees of the
Mississippi. There is a nice pedestrian path, and people walking their dogs,
and New Orleans ne'er-do-wells. It is really nice!
&lt;img alt="bywater" src="articles/transit/images/bywater.jpg" title="A pleasant levee walk"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyways, the moral is: walk along more levees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Distance: 13 miles&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Would I do it again? Only along the Mississippi.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe data-city="no" src=/visualization/airports/leaflet_airport.html?lat=29.9690&amp;lon=-90.1624&amp;zoom=12 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New York (JFK)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one also took two attempts.
In the first try, I started at the Jamaica AirTrain station and walked towards midtown
Manhattan. The roads I took were arterials, and I ran out of time, so hopped on the subway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my next attempt, I started from JFK proper, and spent most of the time
in Brooklyn. It was mostly...uneventful.
The Jamaica sewage plant smells bad. I had avocado toast in Crown Heights.
Tourists on the Brooklyn Bridge made the last 30 minutes exceedingly slow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Distance: 15 miles&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Would I do it again? Yes, given enough time.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe data-city="nyu" src=/visualization/airports/leaflet_airport.html?lat=40.7194&amp;lon=-73.9000&amp;zoom=12 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Buses are bosons, or How I learned to stop worrying and love AC Transit (Part two)</title><link href="/bus-bunching-2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-04-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ian Rose</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-04-24:/bus-bunching-2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="bunch" src="/articles/transit/images/6-bunch.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="6-bunch" src="articles/transit/images/6-bunch.jpg" title="Bunching on the 6 bus line in Oakland"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second and final part of a short series of articles
on constructing a mathematical model for why buses always seem to travel in packs
(known as bus bunching).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="bus-bunching-1.html"&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt;
we set up the model, consisting of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; buses traveling on a loop,
where we parameterized the position of the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(n\)&lt;/span&gt;th bus by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta_n\)&lt;/span&gt;.
We presumed that a bus is slowed down by the boarding of passengers,
and that more passengers will need to board if it has been longer
since the last bus came along, an effect given by a parameter &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\gamma\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The equations for this model are given by
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d\theta_n}{d t} = 
 v_0 \left[ 1 - \gamma (\theta_{n+1} - \theta_n) \right]
\label{evolution}
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We furthermore showed that the equilibrium configuration for a set of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; buses
is for them to be equally spaced along the route, traveling at a velocity of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_e\)&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
v_e = v_0 \left[ 1 - \frac{2 \pi \gamma}{N} \right]
\label{equilibrium}
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In system with five buses, and in reference frame traveling at a velocity of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_e\)&lt;/span&gt;,
this equilibrium solution looks like this:
&lt;iframe src=/visualization/bus/bus-bunching.html?interactive=false&amp;equilibrium=true&amp;boost=true&amp;gamma=0.15&amp;n=5 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article we will demonstrating that this equilibrium solution is not stable,
and that it will inevitably result in the buses bunching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stability analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most stability analyses are centered on answering a central question:
is my equilibrium solution stable with respect to small perturbations?
That is to say, if I have an equilibrium solution and poke it slightly,
does it return to equilibrium, or does that poke keep growing until the solution
is no longer anything like the equilibrium one?
&lt;img alt="stability" src="articles/transit/images/stability.png" title="Illustration of stability"&gt;
This behavior can be visualized by thinking of a ball balanced on a hill,
and another resting in a trough.
Both of the balls are not moving around, and are thus in equilibrium solutions.
However, if I nudge the ball on the hill, it will continue rolling until it is far from the peak.
If I nudge the ball in the trough, it will roll back to the middle and
eventually come to a rest.
The first situation is an unstable equilibrium, and the second is a stable one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our approach for analyzing the system of equations in equation \eqref{evolution} will be similar:
we will investigate its behavior when we nudge it slightly away from the equilibrium solution
represented by equation \eqref{equilibrium}.
If those nudges grow in time, it is unstable.
If they die off in time, it is stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Perturbation equations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step in deriving the perturbation equations is to split the
bus positions &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta_n(t)\)&lt;/span&gt; into two parts, an equilibrium part and a perturbation:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\theta_n = \theta^e_n + \theta^\prime_n
\label{decompose}
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In equation \eqref{decompose}, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta^e_n\)&lt;/span&gt; is the equilibrium solution for the buses
(i.e. &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_e\)&lt;/span&gt; integrated with respect to time),
and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta^\prime_n\)&lt;/span&gt; is a small perturbation away from that equilibrium.
You may wonder what the perturbation actually &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;, since it can be a function of time,
and each of the buses can have a different perturbation.
Fortunately, we will be able to show that this analysis does not depend on the form
of the perturbation (other than that it is nonzero), so it can be completely arbitrary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The governing equations are in terms of velocities rather than positions,
so we take the time derivative of equation \eqref{decompose},
noting that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(d \theta^e_n / dt = v^e\)&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d \theta_n}{dt} = \frac{d \theta^e_n}{dt} + \frac{d \theta^\prime_n}{dt} = v_e + \frac{d \theta^\prime_n}{dt}
\label{decompose2}
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can substitute equations \eqref{decompose} and \eqref{decompose2}
into equation \eqref{evolution} to get
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d \theta^\prime_n}{dt} + v_e = 
v_0 \left[ 1 - \gamma (\theta^e_{n+1} - \theta^e_n) - \gamma(\theta^\prime_{n+1} - \theta^\prime_n) \right]
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Note that in the equilibrium configuration the buses are equally spaced,
so &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta^e_{n+1} - \theta^e_{n} = 2 \pi / N\)&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d \theta^\prime_n}{dt} + v_e = 
v_0 \left[ 1 - \frac{2 \pi \gamma}{N}  - \gamma(\theta^\prime_{n+1} - \theta^\prime_n) \right]
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This allows &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_e\)&lt;/span&gt; to be subtracted from both sides, leaving us with:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d \theta^\prime_n}{dt} = 
v_0 \gamma(\theta^\prime_{n} - \theta^\prime_{n+1})
\label{perturb}
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so what did those manipulations buy us?
There are two attractive features that equation \eqref{perturb} has:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is now a system of differential equations involving only the perturbations,
the time evolution of which we are interested in for the stability problem.
The equilibrium solution has completely disappeared.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More importantly, &lt;em&gt;it is now a system of linear equations!&lt;/em&gt;
There are no nonlinearities or constant offsets getting in our way.
And if there is one thing mathematics is good at analyzing, it is linear equations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, since it is a set of linear equations,
we can write it using matrix notation:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d \Theta^\prime}{d t} = 
\mathbf{A}\Theta^\prime
\label{matrix}
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
where &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\Theta^\prime\)&lt;/span&gt; is a vector containing all the perturbations to the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; buses,
and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{A}\)&lt;/span&gt; is a matrix describing the linear coupling between the buses, given by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\mathbf{A} = 
v_0 \gamma 
\begin{bmatrix}
1 &amp;amp; -1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; \ldots &amp;amp; 0 \\
0 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; -1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; \ldots &amp;amp; 0 \\
0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; -1 &amp;amp; \ldots &amp;amp; 0 \\
\vdots &amp;amp; \vdots &amp;amp; \vdots &amp;amp; \vdots &amp;amp; \ddots &amp;amp; \vdots \\
-1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; \ldots &amp;amp; 1\\
\end{bmatrix}
\label{A}
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Note that the last row couples the speed of the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt;th bus to the first bus,
reflecting the circular nature of the model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The eigendecomposition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When analyzing a system of linear equations,
it is often helpful consider it in terms of its eigenvalues and eigenvectors
(exactly how it is helpful should be clearer in a moment).
A general perturbation vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\Theta^\prime\)&lt;/span&gt; can be decomposed
into a linear combination of the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; eigenvectors of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{A}\)&lt;/span&gt;
(known as an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eigenvalues_and_eigenvectors#Eigenspaces,_geometric_multiplicity,_and_the_eigenbasis_for_matrices"&gt;eigendecomposition&lt;/a&gt;):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\Theta^\prime(t) = \sum_k a_k(t) \Theta^\prime_k
\label{eigs}
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
where &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a_k(t)\)&lt;/span&gt; is the amount of that each eigenvector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\Theta^\prime_k\)&lt;/span&gt;
contributes to the total perturbation &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\Theta^\prime_k(t)\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Substituting equation \eqref{eigs} into \eqref{matrix}, we get
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\sum_k \frac{d a_k}{dt} \Theta^\prime_k = 
\sum_k a_k \mathbf{A}\Theta^\prime_k = 
\sum_k a_k \lambda_k \Theta^\prime_k
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
where we have used the definition of the eigenvalues &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\lambda_k\)&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{A}\Theta^\prime_k = \lambda_k \Theta^\prime_k\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The eigenvectors of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{A}\)&lt;/span&gt; are linearly independent,
so the components of the summation decouple,
giving us a set of independent ordinary differential equations:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d a_k}{d t} = 
\lambda_k a_k
\label{diff_eigen}
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equation \eqref{diff_eigen} looks very much like equation \eqref{matrix},
but with one important difference:
It is now a scalar equation for the time evolution of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a_k\)&lt;/span&gt;.
In fact, it the solution of this ordinary differential equation is among the
first that students of calculus learn to find: an exponential:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
a_k(t) = a_k(0) e^{\lambda_k t}
\label{integrated}
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A hunt for eigenvalues&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equation \eqref{integrated} gives us the solution for the
time evolution of the perturbations of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{A}\)&lt;/span&gt;.
Remember, our perturbation to the equilibrium solution can be written
as a combination of the eigenvectors, and we are interested in whether
the perturbation grows in time or shrinks in time.
The answer to that question all comes down to the values for the eigenvalues &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\lambda_k\)&lt;/span&gt;.
Broadly speaking, there are three possibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\lambda_k\)&lt;/span&gt; is negative. In this case, a perturbation of the shape of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\Theta^\prime_k\)&lt;/span&gt;
will shrink in time, since \eqref{integrated} is a negative exponential.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\lambda_k\)&lt;/span&gt; is positive. In this case, a perturbation of the shape of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\Theta^\prime_k\)&lt;/span&gt;
will grow in time, since \eqref{integrated} is a positive exponential.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\lambda_k\)&lt;/span&gt; is complex. In this case, a perturbation of the shape of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\Theta^\prime_k\)&lt;/span&gt;
will have combined behaviors: it will oscillate according to the imaginary part
of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\lambda_k\)&lt;/span&gt; (due to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euler%27s_formula"&gt;Euler's formula&lt;/a&gt;),
and either shrink or grow according to the sign of the real part.
For our purposes, we want to know it shrinks or grows,
so we are most interested in the real part of any complex eigenvalues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In physical systems, there is always a certain amount of noise,
and in general that noise will put some amount of power
into each of the eigenvectors of the system.
Some eigenvectors might get a bit more power, some might get a bit less,
but for random, uncorrelated noise, we expect all the eigenvectors to get some.
This means that if &lt;em&gt;just one&lt;/em&gt; eigenvalue has a positive real part,
then the power in that eigenvalue will blow up.
Therefore our stability metric is this: &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of the eigenvalues must have
negative real parts for the system to be considered stable to perturbations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let's find the eigenvalues of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{A}\)&lt;/span&gt;.
Usually calculating the eigenvalues of a matrix of a larger order than 2 or 3
is a pretty involved process, but in this case the matrix is
ordered enough, and has enough zeroes in it, that we can come up
with a closed-form solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The eigenvalues of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{A}\)&lt;/span&gt; can be found by solving its
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Characteristic_polynomial"&gt;characteristic polynomial&lt;/a&gt;,
found by taking the determinant of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{A} - \lambda \mathbf{I}\)&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
det(\mathbf{A - \lambda \mathbf{I}}) = 
(v_0 \gamma)^N 
\begin{vmatrix}
1-\lambda &amp;amp; -1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; \ldots &amp;amp; 0 \\
0 &amp;amp; 1-\lambda &amp;amp; -1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; \ldots &amp;amp; 0 \\
0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 1-\lambda &amp;amp; -1 &amp;amp; \ldots &amp;amp; 0 \\
\vdots &amp;amp; \vdots &amp;amp; \vdots &amp;amp; \vdots &amp;amp; \ddots &amp;amp; \vdots \\
-1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; \ldots &amp;amp; 1-\lambda\\
\end{vmatrix}
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We apply the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laplace_expansion"&gt;Laplace expansion&lt;/a&gt;
(where I have elided some steps):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
det(\mathbf{A} - \lambda \mathbf{I}) = 
(v_0 \gamma)^N \left[ (1-\lambda)^N + (-1)(-1)^{N+1}(-1)^{N-1} \right] = 0
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which may be simplified to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
(1-\lambda)^N = 1
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this polynomial equation of order &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; has a fairly straightforward set
of solutions for &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt;: they are the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Root_of_unity"&gt;roots of unity&lt;/a&gt;,
shifted along the positive &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt;-axis by one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can write the solution for &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\lambda_k\)&lt;/span&gt; explicitly
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\lambda_k = e^{\frac{2 k \pi i}{N}} + 1 = \cos \frac{2 k \pi}{N} + i \sin \frac{2 k \pi}{N} + 1
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
which, when plotted (for &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(N=10\)&lt;/span&gt;), gives the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="roots_of_unity" src="articles/transit/images/roots_of_unity.png" title="Eigenvalues of the stability problem"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey, look at that! The real part of each eigenvalue is greater than zero!&lt;sup id="fnref-1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
That is to say, not only is the system unstable, it is &lt;em&gt;wildly&lt;/em&gt; unstable.
Remember, the system is unstable if if &lt;em&gt;just one&lt;/em&gt; of the eigenvalues has a positive real part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Simulating bus bunching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was a long way to go,
but by determining that the eigenvalues of the system of equations \eqref{perturb}
all have nonnegative real parts, we determined that any perturbation
to our equilibrium solution is unstable.
Therefore, if any of the buses on our bus route get slightly off schedule,
they will continue to get further and further off schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's close out the article with some interactive simulations of bus bunching.
The simulations start with a number of buses in the equilibrium configuration,
but as you will see, they soon drift away from that equilibrium, and once they
start to drift, bunching is inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two versions of the simulation: one in the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_e\)&lt;/span&gt; reference frame,
where we see the velocities of the buses relative to their equilibrium velocity,
and one in the street frame, where we see the velocities of the buses relative to the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_e\)&lt;/span&gt; reference frame:
&lt;iframe src=/visualization/bus/bus-bunching.html?interactive=true&amp;equilibrium=false&amp;boost=true&amp;gamma=0.15&amp;n=5 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the street reference frame:
&lt;iframe src=/visualization/bus/bus-bunching.html?interactive=true&amp;equilibrium=false&amp;boost=false&amp;gamma=0.15&amp;n=5 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model we analyzed here was probably about as simple as it could be
while still exhibiting bunching behavior. We used a simplified geometry,
and it really only had two parameters (&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_0\)&lt;/span&gt;, the speed in the absence of passengers,
and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\gamma\)&lt;/span&gt;, the amount by which passenger boarding slows it down).
Nevertheless, it demonstrates a plausible mechanism for an all-too familiar
occurrence for transit riders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is that actual bus system behavior can be more complex than this
simple model: it has drivers, schedulers, and real-time information.
It is possible to design things to mitigate the essential bunchiness of a route.
Things like &lt;a href="https://thesource.metro.net/2017/10/14/all-door-boarding-proposed-for-720-and-754-rapid-lines/"&gt;streamlined passenger boarding&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bus_priority"&gt;signal priority&lt;/a&gt;,
and layovers all likely have a role in mitigating bunching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what's the moral here? I'd like to say that you shouldn't feel frustrated
the next time a pack of buses roll up to your stop, but that's probably not realistic.
Instead, maybe just look at them with grim recognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="18-bunch" src="articles/transit/images/18-bunch.jpg" title="Bunching on the 18 bus line in Albany"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strictly speaking, there is a single eigenvalue that is equal to zero, 
when &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(k=N\)&lt;/span&gt;. You can verify manually that this corresponds to an eigenvector
where each bus is perturbed by the same amount (a &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{1}\)&lt;/span&gt; vector).
A perturbation of this form is marginally stable (neither stable nor unstable),
since none of the buses get any closer to or further from each other.
For the pedantic, you can replace of my statements about all eigenvegors 
being unstable with "all eigenvectors but one are unstable".&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Buses are bosons, or How I learned to stop worrying and love AC Transit (Part one)</title><link href="/bus-bunching-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-03-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ian Rose</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-03-19:/bus-bunching-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="bunch" src="/articles/transit/images/18-bunch.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you have spent any amount of time using mass transit,
you know the frustration of waiting for the better part of an hour for a bus to arrive,
only to see two or three of them roll up in quick succession.
This phenomenon is a common enough problem that it has a name: "bus bunching":&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="18-bunch2" src="articles/transit/images/18-bunch2.jpg" title="Bunching on the 18 bus line in Berkeley"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this two-part series, we'll investigate bus bunching by making a mathematical model of a bus route.
In this first part, we'll construct the model and find it's equilibrium solution.
In the second part, we'll demonstrate the inevitability for that model to bunch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start by constructing a model for the speed of a single bus.
We will assume that the bus has a fixed route, on which it travels all day.
That route may be on any number of different streets, go wending through different
neighborhoods, and generally make very little sense 
(like my beloved &lt;a href="http://www.actransit.org/pdf/maps/version_38/12.pdf"&gt;12 line&lt;/a&gt;).
However, if it travels back and forth on this same route, we can model it as a loop,
and its position on that loop can be mapped to an angle on a circle &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta\)&lt;/span&gt;.
We can then identify the speed of the bus with the time derivative of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest model for &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(d\theta/ dt\)&lt;/span&gt; is for the bus to travel at a constant speed &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_0\)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d \theta}{d t} = v_0
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Or, expressed in a simulation:
&lt;iframe src=/visualization/bus/bus-bunching.html?interactive=false&amp;boost=false&amp;equilibrium=true&amp;gamma=0&amp;n=1 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this model isn't very interesting.
There is only a single bus, and it is traveling at a fixed speed,
so it has no hope of exhibiting the kind of bunching behavior that we want to explain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A typical mass transit route operates multiple buses with a given
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Headway"&gt;headway&lt;/a&gt;,
the distance (or time) between successive vehicles on the route.
If everything is operating according to the plan,
the headway from one bus to the next should be approximately constant,
with possible scheduled variations depending on the time of day
(such as increased frequency during rush hour, or decreased frequency at night).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can increase the complexity of our model adding some more buses so that there are &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; on the route:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d \theta_n}{d t} = v_0
\label{constant}
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this equation the subscript indicates the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(n\)&lt;/span&gt;th bus out of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt;,
so a simulation with five buses looks like this:
&lt;iframe src=/visualization/bus/bus-bunching.html?interactive=false&amp;equilibrium=true&amp;boost=false&amp;gamma=0&amp;n=5 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
Okay, so this is starting to more closely resemble a bus route.
However, the buses are still moving at a constant speed, and have no effect on each other.
In order for our model to exhibit the richer characteristics of a system that can bunch,
there must be some way for their speed to be a function of conditions on the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many factors that can control the speed of a bus traveling through town,
including traffic, construction, scheduled layovers, and the number of passengers.
In order to keep the model simple, we will focus on the last factor:
the number of passengers who board and exit the bus.
A traveling bus constantly picks up and drops off passengers as it makes its way around its route.
This process takes time (as anyone who has watched a passenger fumble with change upon boarding knows).
A bus that boards and deposits more passengers will, in general, make slower progress along its route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many things affect the number of passengers boarding a given bus, 
including time-of-day, scheduling, and population density.
In order to keep the model as simple as possible, we will ignore those and
concentrate on a single factor: the amount of time since the previous bus.
We will assume that as more time passes, more passengers arrive at a bus stop for pickup.
If a bus falls behind schedule, more people will have arrived at each stop,
meaning that it will be further slowed down by the excess passengers.
In the following analysis, we will use the distance between buses as a proxy
for the number of passengers that need to be picked up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to augment our model to account for this slowing-down behavior.
The expression for speed in equation \eqref{constant} is a constant,
so the next-simplest expression is to make it linear in the distance between buses
(our proxy for the number of passengers):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d\theta_n}{d t} = 
 v_0 \left[ 1 - \gamma (\theta_{n+1} - \theta_n) \right]
\label{evolution}
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this equation, a bus picking up &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; passengers travels at &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_0\)&lt;/span&gt;
(which happens if there has been no time for them to accumulate since the previous bus).
As the distance between a bus and the one ahead of it increases,
the speed of the bus slows down, reflecting the additional time spent boarding and disembarking.
The dimensionless parameter &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\gamma\)&lt;/span&gt; determines how sensitive the bus speeds are to differences in headway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equation \eqref{evolution} is a set of ordinary differential equations
(one equation for each of the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; buses).
It will be the primary  evolution equation for our system of buses,
which we will analyze by answering the following two questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there an equilibrium solution to these equations?
That is to say, is there a solution that does not evolve in time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is an equilibrium solution, is it stable?
A stable solution, when perturbed, will return to the equilibrium.
An unstable one will get further and further from equilibrium until the buses are bunched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strictly speaking, an equilibrium solution does not exist for the system of equations as described:
as long as the buses have a nonzero velocity, their positions will evolve in time.
However, with a slight reframing of the question it makes sense to talk about an equilibrium:
is there a configuration for which the bus velocities are constant,
and that the distance between them (headways) are not changing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a coordinate system traveling with the buses at equilibrium speed
the solution to the system would then look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=/visualization/bus/bus-bunching.html?interactive=false&amp;equilibrium=true&amp;boost=true&amp;gamma=0&amp;n=5 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems intuitive that an equilibrium solution, if it exists,
should have the buses equally spaced, so let's start looking for a solution of that form.
Let's further guess that the equilibrium velocity is the base bus speed &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_0\)&lt;/span&gt;.
A change of coordinates makes this system a bit easier to reason about.
Let's boost ourselves into moving a coordinate system &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\psi\)&lt;/span&gt;, defined by:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\psi_n \equiv \theta_n - v_0 t
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this we can also get the relations
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d\theta_n}{d t} =
\frac{d \psi_n}{d t} + v_0
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\theta_n =
\psi_n + v_0 t
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Substituting these into equation \eqref{evolution},
we get the governing equations in terms of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\psi_n\)&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d \psi_n}{d t} + v_0 = 
v_0 \left[ 1 - \gamma (\psi_{n+1} - \psi_n) \right]
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d \psi_n}{d t} = 
v_0 \gamma (\psi_{n} - \psi_{n+1})
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the buses are equally spaced around the loop, then the distance
between them is the whole loop length divided between the number of buses, or
&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\psi_{n+1} - \psi_n = 2 \pi/N\)&lt;/span&gt;,
which makes the governing equations in the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\psi\)&lt;/span&gt; coordinates&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d \psi_n}{d t} = 
\frac{ 2 \pi v_0 \gamma }{N}
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless the interaction term &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\gamma\)&lt;/span&gt; is zero, the time evolution of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\psi_n\)&lt;/span&gt; is nonzero,
making this configuration a non-equilibrium solution to the system.
Therefore, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_0\)&lt;/span&gt; is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the equilibrium velocity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should make sense, as we defined &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_0\)&lt;/span&gt; to be the speed of the bus
in the absence of any delays due to loading and unloading of passengers.
When we include that delay, the buses will be slower.
Instead, let's construct a speed for buses that takes into account the
delay due to passengers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again we presume that the buses are equally spaced,
such that the distance between them is &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(2 \pi/N\)&lt;/span&gt;.
Then, given the evolution equation \eqref{evolution}, we can calculate the speed &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_e\)&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
v_e = \frac{d \theta_n}{d_t} = v_0 \left[ 1 - \frac{2 \pi \gamma}{N} \right]
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let's boost into a &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; coordinate system &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\phi\)&lt;/span&gt;, defined by
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\phi_n \equiv \theta_n - v_e t
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Substituting this into equation \eqref{evolution}, we find&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d \phi_n}{d t} + v_e =
v_0 \left[ 1 - \gamma \left(\phi_{n+1} - \phi_n \right) \right]
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As before, when the buses are equally spaced, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\phi_{n+1} - \phi_n = 2 \pi/N\)&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d \phi_n}{d t} + v_e =
v_0 \left[ 1 - \frac{2 \pi \gamma}{N}  \right]
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The right-hand-side is exactly &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_e\)&lt;/span&gt;, so we can subtract it from both sides to get&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation}
\frac{d \phi_n}{d t} = 0
\end{equation}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is exactly what we wanted: in the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\phi\)&lt;/span&gt; coordinate system,
the positions of the buses are constant in time, so
equally-spaced buses are all in equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to get a feel for the equilibrium solution,
you can experiment with this interactive simulation, which shows the buses
traveling at their equilibrium speed and spacing
(in the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\phi\)&lt;/span&gt; coordinate system that moves with them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=/visualization/bus/bus-bunching.html?interactive=true&amp;equilibrium=true&amp;boost=true&amp;gamma=0.15&amp;n=5 width=700 height=700&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that as the number of buses increases and the headway between the buses gets smaller,
the equilibrium speed increases, reflecting the decreased number of passengers each has to pick up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point we have answered the first of the two above questions: there is an equilibrium solution.
In the next installment of this series, we are going to answer the second question:
is this equilibrium solution stable? (Spoiler: it's not.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="streetcar" src="/articles/transit/images/streetcar-bunch.jpg" title="New Orleans streetcars can be bunched too"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content></entry></feed>